Ames Family Papers, 1812-2012
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
George A. Plimpton was born in New York on March 18, 1927, the eldest child of Pauline Ames Plimpton and Francis T.P. Plimpton. He was educated at Phillips Exeter Academy and at Harvard (B.A. 1950), and went on to earn a second B.A. at King's College, Cambridge. He was married first to Freddy Espy, with whom he had two children, Medora and Taylor; the marriage ended in divorce and he later married Sarah Dudley, with whom he had twin daughters, Lauren and Olivia. Plimpton co-founded The Paris Review in 1953 with Harold L. Humes and Peter Matthiesson, whom he met while at Cambridge, and served as that magazine's editor until his death. Plimpton came into his own as a writer after publishing the widely acclaimed books Out of My League (1961) and Paper Lion (1966), based on his experiences as a temporary guest member of professional baseball and football teams, respectively. He successfully pursued this unique form of participatory journalism by entering a match against boxing champion, Archie Moore; playing percussion for Leonard Bernstein and the New York Philharmonic; swinging from a trapeze in a circus's big tent; and playing golf in a pro tournament, bridge with professionals, and tennis with Poncho Gonzales. He acted in several films and served, unofficially, as New York's first Fireworks Commissioner. Plimpton, a long-time friend of the Kennedy family, was with Bobby Kennedy when he was assassinated and, in the ensuing chaos, helped subdue Sirhan Sirhan. Genial and well-liked, he was famous for the parties he frequently gave in his home above The Paris Review offices in New York. George A. Plimpton died in New York on September 26, 2003.
The Ames Family Papers consist of 78 linear feet of biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, artwork, writings, photographs, and printed materials dating from 1812 to 2012. The bulk of the collection pertains to suffragist and early birth control advocate, Blanche Ames Ames, and to her father, Civil War general Adelbert Ames; the papers of her daughter, Pauline Ames Plimpton, are also significant in volume. Other family members are included through their biographical materials, correspondence and, in some cases, their writings. There is also considerable genealogical information about the extended Ames and Butler families, compiled primarily by Blanche Butler Ames and added to over time by other family members, that traces the family's roots back to its European origins.
Correspondence comprises a large part of the collection and reveals the inner workings of numerous primary family relationships, as well as offering insight into the moral, social, and political climates through a long continuum of U.S. history. Of particular interest are the courtship letters of Blanche Butler Ames and Adelbert Ames, Blanche Ames Ames and Oakes Ames, and Pauline Ames Plimpton and Francis T.P. Plimpton, as well as life-long correspondence between these couples after they married. Letters among several sets of mothers, daughters and sisters are also significant, especially in that they span the entire lives of the individuals concerned.
The military careers of Benjamin Franklin Butler and Adelbert Ames are well documented in the portions of the collection pertaining to them. Legal documents relevant to numerous lawsuits in which Butler was involved may also be of interest to scholars of legal history. Further information about Adelbert Ames is located in the papers of his daughter, Blanche Ames Ames, who researched and wrote Adelbert Ames: Broken Oaths and Reconstruction in Mississippi, 1835-1933 in defense of his political career in Mississippi during Reconstruction, and in SERIES V. CLIPPINGS.
The papers of Blanche Ames Ames contain significant materials about the early birth control movement, especially the Massachusetts Birth Control League. There is also some information about Margaret Sanger and about other birth control organizations, including the American Birth Control League, in this portion of the collection. Documents generated during Ames's tenure as board member and as president of the New England Hospital for Women and Children in Boston are included, as well. Blanche Ames Ames's papers contain information about her career as an amateur artist, including drawings and sketches of family and friends, and information about the System of Color Theory. There is a small amount of material about the suffrage movement, notably political cartoons by Ames and others. Ames' papers also shed considerable light on her involvement in the career of her husband, Oakes Ames.
Pauline Ames Plimpton wrote several books about various members of the Plimpton family, which document much of that family's history, and the bulk of that information is located in her papers. Materials about the life of noted literary figure and editor of The Paris Review, George A. Plimpton, are also included in the collection.
The history of various pieces of real estate owned by the Ames family in the U.S. and in Europe is well documented, most significantly that of Borderland, the North Easton, Massachusetts home of Blanche Ames Ames and Oakes Ames, and the Villa Balbianello on Lake Como in Italy. There are also files pertaining to Bay View, a compound of summer cottages in Gloucester, Massachusetts; the Whim, the family's winter retreat in Ormond, Florida; and several Boston-area residences. Photographs of these properties are located in SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS.
The bulk of the papers date from 1861 to 1995 and focus primarily on the Civil War, Reconstruction, birth control, suffrage, and the personal and professional lives of members of the Ames family. Types of material include correspondence, diaries, writings, speeches, legal documents, photographs, journal articles, newspaper clippings, memorabilia, and printed sources.
The papers are arranged in five series:
SERIES I. FAMILY HISTORY
SERIES II. REAL ESTATE
SERIES III. INDIVIDUALS
SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
SERIES V. CLIPPINGS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
APPENDIX: Genealogy
AMES FAMILY - Oakes Ames branch
Generation I. Oliver Ames I (1779-1863) m. Susanna Angier (1783-1847)
Generation II. Issue of Oliver Ames and Susanna Angier Ames
Oakes Ames (1804-1873) m. Evelina Gilmore
Oliver Ames II (1807-1877) m. Sarah Lothrop
Generation III. Issue of Oakes Ames and Evelina Gilmore Ames
Oakes Angier Ames (1829-1918)
Oliver Ames III (1831-1895) m. Anna Coffin Ray
Frank Morton Ames (1833-1898)
Susan Eveline Ames (1842-1890)
Issue of Oliver Ames II and Sarah Lothrop Ames
Frederick Lothrop Ames (1835-1893)
Helen Angier Ames (1836-1882)
Generation IV. Issue of Oliver Ames III and Ann Coffin Ray Ames
Anna Lee Ames (1864-1934) m. George M. Nowell
Evelina Orville Ames (b.1863)
Lilian Ames (1870-1925) m. ? Zaiss
Oakes Ames (1974-1950) m. Blanche Ames
Susan Evelyn Ames (b. 1867) m. Frederick F. Hall
William Hadwen Ames (1861-1918) m. Mary Elizabeth Hodges (widowed; second wife = Fannie Elizabeth Holt)
AMES FAMILY - Blanche Ames Ames branch
Generation II. Jesse Ames (1804-1894) m Martha Tolman (1813-1904)
Generation III. Issue of Jesse Ames and Martha Tolman Ames
Adelbert Ames (1835-1933) m. Blanche Butler (1847-1939)
BUTLER FAMILY
Generation I. John Butler (1782-1819) m. Charlotte Ellison
Generation II. Issue of John and Charlotte Ellison Butler
Benjamin F. Butler (1818-1893) m. Sarah Hildreth
Generation III. Issue of Benjamin F. and Sarah H. Butler
Ben-Israel Butler
Blanche Butler (1847-1939) m. Adelbert Ames (1835-1933)
Paul Butler m. Joanna ?
Generation IV. Issue of Adelbert Ames and Blanche Butler Ames
Adelbert Ames, Jr. (1880-1955) m. Fanny Hazen (b. 1887)
Blanche Ames (1879-1969) m. Oakes Ames (1874-1950)
Butler Ames (1871-1954) m. Fifille Willis (1884-1940)
Edith Ames (1873-1958) m. C. Brooks Stevens (1864-1949)
Sarah Ames (1874-1931) m. Spencer Borden (1872-1937)
Jessie Ames (1882-1967) m. Andrew Marshall (1879-1965)
Generation V. Issue of Adelbert Ames, Jr. and Fanny Hazen
Adelbert Ames III (b. 1921) m. Judith Derby (1923-1973)
Priscilla Ames (b. 1924) m. Melvin Anderson (b. 1920)
Issue of Blanche Ames Ames and Oakes Ames
Amyas Ames (1906-2000 ) m. Evelyn Ingeborg Perkins (1908-1990) (widowed; second wife = Lucia Millham)
Evelyn Ames (1910-1993 ) m. J.P. Davis (1908-1977)
Oliver Ames (1903-1971) m. Ellen Moseley (b. 1919)
Pauline Ames (1901-1995) m. Francis T. P. Plimpton (1900-1984)
Generation V. Issue of Edith Ames Stevens and C. Brooks Stevens
Ames Stevens (b. 1897) m. Phyllis Brooks (1897-1977)
Edith Stevens (b. 1899) m. John P. Stevens (1897-1976)
Harriet Stevens (b. 1900) m. A. Alexander Robey (1898-1975)
Brooks Stevens, Jr. (b. 1902) m. Janet Hubbard (1904-1977)
Issue of Sarah Ames Borden and Spencer Borden
Blanche Borden (b. 1902) m. Alfred Frenning (1900-1966)
Ames Borden (1908-1926)
Richard Borden (b. 1920) m. Elizabeth McGinley (b. 1913) divorced; second wife = Bearowice Brown (b. 1921)
Joan Borden (b. 1907) m. Leonard Colt (1900-1975)
Issue of Jessie Ames Marshall and Andrew Marshall
Andrew Marshall, Jr. (b. 1912) m. Lee McLean (1914-1943) widowed; second wife = Margaret Sayre (b 1913)
Blanche Marshall (b. 1915) m. John McLane, Jr. (b. 1916) divorced; second husband = Jerome Bruner (b. 1915)
Jessie Marshall (b. 1916) m. Ben Williams, Jr. (b. 1915)
Malcolm Marshall (b. 1919) m. Andy Rass-Dilley (b. 1930)
Generation VI. Issue of Amyas Ames and Evelyn Perkins Ames
Edward Ames (b. 1933) m. Sue Holtz (b. 1937)
Joan Ames (b. 1942) m. John Woodcock (b. 1940)
Oakes Ames (b. 1931) m. Louise Kimball (b. 1932)
Olivia Ames (b. 1937) m. Harrison Hoblitzelle (b.1923)
Issue of Evelyn Ames Davis and J.P. Davis
Ames Davis (b. 1945) m. Susan Ivie (b. 1945)
Blanche Davis (b. 1934) m. Robert Matthews (b. 1929)
Evelyn Davis (b. 1941) m. Emilio Pittarelli (b. 1932)
John P. Davis (b. 1936) m. M. Dee Walker (b. 1936)
Issue of Oliver Ames and Ellen Moseley Ames
Angier Ames (b. 1947) m. Julie Huggard
Oliver Ames, Jr. (b. 1945) m. Mary Oleksiw (b. 1943)
Thomas Ames (b. 1952)
Generation VI. Issue of Pauline Ames Plimpton and Francis T. P. Plimpton
Francis T.P. Plimpton, Jr. (b. 1928) m. Susan Wadsworth (b. 1931)
George Ames Plimpton (1927-2003) m. Freddy M. Espy (b. 1941) divorced: second wife = Sarah Dudley
Oakes Ames Plimpton (b. 1933) m. Patricia Magee
Sarah Gay Plimpton (b. 1936)
Issue of Harriet Stevens and A. Alexander Robey
A. Alexander Robey, Jr. (b. 1924) m. Nancy Hurlburt (b. 1926)
Harriet L. Robey (b. 1932) m. William A. Myers (b. 1929)
Issue of Ames Stevens and Phyllis Brooks Stevens
Edward B. Stevens (b. 1922) m. Ann C. Johnson (b. 1923)
Issue of Edith Stevens Stevens and John P. Stevens, Jr.
Phebe T. Stevens (b. 1923) m. Joshua L. Miner III (b. 1920)
Issue of Blanche Borden Frenning and Alfred B. Frenning
Blanche Frenning (b. 1929) m. Edward P. Srowater (b.1924)
Generation VII: Issue of Francis T.P. Plimpton, Jr. and Susan Wadsworth Plimpton
Peter A. Plimpton (b. 1955)
Jane W. Plimpton (b. 1959)
Issue of George A. Plimpton and Freddy Espy Plimpton
Medora A. Plimpton (b. 1971)
Taylor Plimpton
Issue of George A. Plimpton and Sarah Dudley Plimpton (second wife)
Lauren Plimpton and Olivia Plimpton (twins)
Issue of Oakes A. Plimpton and Patricia Magee Plimpton
Robin Plimpton
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Blanche Ames Ames gave the first installment of her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1968, shortly before she died, and her four children added to the collection after her death in 1969. In 1978 the Commonwealth of Massachusetts donated Blanche Ames Ames papers that had remained in storage at the Ames family home, Borderland, after it became a state park in 1971. Pauline Ames Plimpton continued to augment the collection and encouraged the family to do the same; her son, Oakes A. Plimpton, donated her papers after her death in 1995. The Massachusetts Department of Conservation and Recreation donated additional materials from Borderland in 2013. Numerous other family members have added their own papers, as well as documents pertaining to their relatives. Other donors of record include Evelyn Ames Davis, Sarah Gay Plimpton, and Harriet Robey.
Search Terms
Ames family; Ames family--Homes and haunts--Massachusetts; Butler family; Plimpton family; Ames, Adelbert, 1835-1933; Ames, Blanche; Ames, Blanche Butler, 1845-1939; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893; Butler, Sarah Hildreth, d. 1876; Plimpton, Francis T.P. (Francis Taylor Pearsons), 1900-1983; Plimpton, Pauline Ames, 1901-1995; Borderland (North Easton, Mass.); New England Hospital for Women and Children--History--Sources; North Easton (Mass.)--History--20th century--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Birth control--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Courtship--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Marriage--United States--History; Physiological optics--History--Sources; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)--Mississippi--Personal narratives; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives; Voyages and travel--History--Sources; Women artists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women inventors--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--Suffrage--Caricatures and cartoons--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--Massachusetts--History--Sources
Related Material
There are related collections in the Sophia Smith Collection and at other institutions as follows:
Papers of extended Ames and Butler families at the Easton Historical Society, North Easton, Mass.; and Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Papers of Oakes Ames and Oliver Ames at the Massachusetts State Archives, Boston, Massachusetts; and Union Pacific Railroad Co., Omaha, Nebraska.
Papers of Oliver Ames III at the Stonehill Industrial History Center, Stonehill College, Easton, Massachusetts.
Benjamin F. Butler Papers at the Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Blanche Ames Ames Papers in the Smith College Archives; Smith College Museum of Art; and Schlesinger Library, Harvard University; and in the Sophia Smith Collection, the following papers related to Blanche Ames Ames: Florence Rose papers, Garrison family papers, Margaret Sanger papers, New England Hospital for Women and Children records, Planned Parenthood Federation of America records, and Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts records.
Oakes Ames Papers at the Arnold Arboretum Library and Archives, Jamaica Plain, Mass.; Boston Athenaeum, Boston, Mass.; University Archives, Harvard University; Oakes Ames Orchid Herbarium, Harvard University; Lundell Rare Book Library, University of Texas at Dallas.
Pauline Ames Plimpton Papers in the Smith College Archives.
Francis T. P. Plimpton and Plimpton family papers at Columbia University.
- SERIES I. FAMILY HISTORY (1859-2004), 1 linear ft.
  This series consists of historical and genealogical information about the Ames and Butler families, and includes correspondence, notes, family trees, directories, books, clippings, and newsletters. Further materials pertaining to specific individuals are located primarily in SERIES III. INDIVIDUALS.
- SERIES II. REAL ESTATE (1891-1994), 3.5 linear ft.
  The nine subseries are listed alphabetically either by property name or by the town or city in which it is, or was, located.
  This series contains information about various properties owned by the extended Ames and Butler families. The nine subseries are listed alphabetically either by property name or by the town or city in which it is, or was, located: Bay View, Borderland, Boston, Highland Meadows, Oakes Ames Memorial Hall, The Whim, Winthrop Ames Mansion, Miscellaneous U.S. Real Estate, and Villa Balbianello. The histories of Borderland, now a Massachusetts state park, and Villa Balbianello, now owned by the Italian government, are documented particularly well. Types of materials include correspondence, contracts and leases, deeds, floor plans, drawings, maps, financial information, and reports. Information that is limited to the residences of nuclear families (as opposed to family compounds, jointly owned properties, or real estate ultimately taken over by state or national governments) is located in SERIES III. INDIVIDUALS. Photographs of many of the buildings and grounds described in this series may be found in SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS.
- SERIES III. INDIVIDUALS (1812-2012), 56.75 linear ft.
  This series is arranged first by generation and then alphabetically by last name.
  This series comprises the bulk of the collection, and is arranged first by generation and then alphabetically by last name. Spouses follow directly after the member of the Ames and Butler families to whom they are, or were, married. Correspondence in this series is voluminous and is filed primarily by author. However, the papers of some individuals contain both outgoing and incoming correspondence, when the total volume of a correspondent's papers did not warrant a discrete subseries for that person. In addition to correspondence, this series contains biographical and financial information and, particularly in the papers of Blanche Butler Ames, Blanche Ames Ames and Pauline Ames Plimpton, extensive files about their writings. The papers of Blanche Ames Ames richly document the early years of the Massachusetts Birth Control League and related organizations; files pertaining to her suffrage activities, including the cartoons in the Art subseries, are also noteworthy. Related materials about most individuals in this series are located in SERIES I. FAMILY HISTORY, SERIES II. REAL ESTATE, and SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS; further information about civil, cultural, military and political issues of interest to Adelbert Ames may be found in SERIES V. CLIPPINGS.
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS (1855-1993), 6.5 linear ft.
  This series contains most of the photographs pertaining to the Ames and Butler families, with the following exceptions: Photographs originally found in Blanche Ames Ames's Smith College scrapbook are filed in her biographical subseries, and photographs relating to books are filed with the individual author's papers. The three subseries follow exactly the arrangement of the first three primary series: Family history, Real estate, and Individuals. The Real estate and Individuals subseries are extensive and contain formal portraits as well as casual photographs of the family at work and at play.
- SERIES V. CLIPPINGS (1852-1904), 3.25 linear ft.
  This series consists entirely of newspaper clippings cut by Adelbert Ames from unidentified newspapers. The clippings, some of which are annotated, document a variety of subjects of particular interest to Ames and also provide a unique overview of national and international politics and culture over more than half a century.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS (1865-1995, undated), 7 linear ft.
- SERIES I. FAMILY HISTORY
  - Gift agreement for watercolors by Blanche and Oakes Ames, 7 Nov 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Union Catalog of Manuscript Collections: report, 1976 (Box 1)
  - List of holdings in Schlesinger Library, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings and pamphlet, 1958-94, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Genealogies
    - Ames, Butler, and Hildreth families
      - Correspondence re: tracing family lines, 1894-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Family trees, 1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
        [see also Oversize Materials]
      - Ames family directories, 1958-94 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
      - Society of Mayflower Descendents: certificate and pamphlets, 1955-62 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Eames, Anthony and Mark: typed excerpts from public records and published books, and related correspondence, 1897, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Notes on Ames family genealogy, compiled by Blanche Butler Ames, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
      - Ames family reunion
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1988-89 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Programs and reminiscences, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Butler family genealogies and newsletters, 1874, 1979-93, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Books
        - Origin and Genealogy of the Hildreth Family, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Genealogies
    - Ames, Butler, and Hildreth families
      - Books (continued)
        - Harriet Hildreth Heard by "her daughter Hildreth," 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Biographical Sketch of Israel Hildreth, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Other family branches: correspondence, notes, and related documents
      - Badcock/Babcock, Barber/Barbour, Barstow, and Bullard, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Calderwood and Cutter, 1894-96, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Ellison, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Fisher, Fuller, Hill, and Howland, 1898-1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Ingraham, 1894-96, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Keen, 1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Leland, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Perry, 1891-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Smith, 1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Tolman, 1897-1900, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Williams and Wooster, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Summary of facts relating to death of Frederick L. Ames, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Whim (family newsletter)
    - Published issues, 1993-2008 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence and drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-64, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    [see also Oversize Materials and Box 136]
- SERIES II. REAL ESTATE
  - Bay View
    [see also SERIES III: INDIVIDUALS - Generation V - Robey, Harriet Stevensand SERIES IV: PHOTOGRAPHS]
    - General, 1904-80, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1914-42 (Box 3, Folder 1A-3)
    - Beach Realty Trust
      - Correspondence, memoranda, and legal documents, 1925-93, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Annual report, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Borderland
    [see also SERIES III: INDIVIDUALS - Generation VI - Plimpton, Oakes A., SERIES IV: PHOTOGRAPHS, and OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - Floor plans, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Friends of Borderland
      - Advisory Council: minutes, 1977-87 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Board of Directors: minutes, 1984-94 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Newsletters, 1984-94 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1984-94, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Dispute with Thomas Hind Co.: correspondence and bills, 1928-33 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - General correspondence, memoranda, and notes, 1914-94, undated (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Land use maps and instructions, 1948 (Box 3A, Folder 1)
    - Game farm: correspondence and financial materials, 1913-48 (Box 3A, Folder 2)
    - Accounts and ledgers, 1912-54 (Box 3A, Folder 3)
    - Inventory of library holdings, undated (Box 3A, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlets and brochures, 1973, undated (Box 3A, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1974-88, undated (Box 3A, Folder 6)
  - Boston
    - Bay State Road: Charles River Basin Fill: blueprints, correspondence, reports, and notes, 1931-32, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 231 Bay State Road: correspondence and notes, 1928-49, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 355 Commonwealth Ave., Boston, Mass.: correspondence, appraisals, and floor plan, 1899, 1919, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Highland, New Jersey: correspondence and contracts, 1891-1906, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    [see also SERIES IV: PHOTOGRAPHS]
  - Meadow Lakes (location unknown): correspondence, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Oakes Ames Memorial Hall (North Easton, Massachusetts)
    - Correspondence, notes, plans, reports, and receipts, 1961-82, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-11)
      [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - Clippings, 1963-94 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Whim (Ormond, Florida)
    - General,1975-89 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1924-68, undated (Box 4, Folder 14-17)